Dallas Smythe fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Publications and presentations, 1936 - 1992; F-16-6; 1.77 m of textual records; Physical description: 7 photographs located in F-16-6-2-1
  - Publications correspondence, 1952 - 1992; F-16-6-2; 25 cm of textual records 7 photographs: black and white; 20x25 cm; Physical description: 7 photographs located in F-16-6-2-1
    - The relevance of United States legislative - regulatory experience to the Canadian telecommunications situation, 1970; F-16-6-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 16-41)
    - Manuscript on mass communications in Yugoslavia, 1974; F-16-6-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 16-41)
    - The writing of Dependency Road, 1978 - 1980; F-16-6-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 16-41)
    - Book on the political economy of the radio spectrum, 1980 - 1981; F-16-6-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 16-41)
    - Book on the critical theory of the political economy of communications, 1980 - 1983; F-16-6-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 16-41)
    - Reviews of Dependency Road, 1980 - 1984; F-16-6-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 16-41)
    - Telecommunications training program for officials in developing countries, 1982 - 1984; F-16-6-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 16-42)
    - Radio spectrum article for the International Encyclopedia of Communications, 1984 - 1986; F-16-6-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 16-42)
    - The State, 1984 - 1987; F-16-6-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 16-42)
    - General correspondence re publications, 1964 - 1992; F-16-6-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 16-42)
    - Ablex Publishing Corporation - publication of Dependency Road, 1980 - 1992; F-16-6-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 16-42)
- Teaching, 1913 - 1987; F-16-7; 48 cm of textual records
  Dallas Smythe served as a professor and/or guest lecturer at several universities from 1948 to 1988, including the University of Illinois; the University of Saskatchewan at Regina; the University of California, San Diego; Simon Fraser University; Temple University; Ohio State University; and the University of Hawaii. Smythe also participated in teach-ins on the topics of the Vietnam War, Reaganomics, and other subjects. He was also involved in research and lecturing at the Centre for International Research on Communications and Information Technology (CIRCIT) in Sydney, Australia.
  Series consists of records arising from Smythe's teaching activities at various locations. Series includes course outlines, lecture notes, reference material, class readings, and other materials. The majority of the records in this series relate to courses on the political economy of communications, and other topics in the field of communications.
  - Economics of communications exam questions, 1950 - 1957; F-16-7-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Communications 467/468 - political economy of communications bibliography, 1956 - 1957; F-16-7-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Communication 471 - proseminar in communications, 1957 - 1959; F-16-7-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Communication 467 - political economy of communications, 1961; F-16-7-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Weekly papers and assignments, 1960 - 1963; F-16-7-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Communications 468 - political economy of communications, 1963; F-16-7-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - General notes and lectures, 1962 - 1963; F-16-7-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Teach-ins, 1958 - 1965; F-16-7-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Economics 368 outline - political economy of communications, 1965 - 1966; F-16-7-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Log of economics 368, 1965 - 1966; F-16-7-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Economics 392 - political economy of communications II, 1967; F-16-7-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Economics 391 - political economy of communications, 1966 - 1967; F-16-7-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Economics 391 preparation - political economy of communications, 1965 - 1967; F-16-7-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Economics 862 - Spring 1969, 1966 - 1969; F-16-7-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Economics 381/861 - political economy of communications, 1969 - 1970; F-16-7-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Communications 841 - the art of communications, 1967 - 1971; F-16-7-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Political economy of communications - readings 1, 1913 - 1972; F-16-7-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 16-43)
  - Political economy of communications - readings 2, 1937 - 1970; F-16-7-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Political economy of communications, 1973; F-16-7-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - University of California, San Diego course materials, 1973; F-16-7-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - General course outlines and reading lists, 1961 - 1974; F-16-7-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Course outlines and readings for the political economy of communications, 1966 - 1974; F-16-7-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Communications 834 - political economy of communications, 1976; F-16-7-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Communications 840 - history of communications theory, 1975 - 1976; F-16-7-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Lectures - Australia, 1962 - 1976; F-16-7-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Communications 100, 1976 - 1977; F-16-7-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Capitalism, communications, and development lectures, 1970 - 1977; F-16-7-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Communications 234 - political economy of communications, 1977 - 1980; F-16-7-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 16-44)
  - Communications 130 - mass communications, spring 1979, F-16-7-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 130 - mass communications, fall 1979, F-16-7-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 240 - political economy of communications, 1979; F-16-7-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, 1978 - 1980; F-16-7-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 340 - political economy of the radio spectrum and telecommunications, 1978 - 1980; F-16-7-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 880 - seminar in international communications, Temple University, 1980; F-16-7-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Radio-television-film 530e - political economy of mass communications, Temple University, 1981; F-16-7-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Radio-television-film 860 - public policy, Temple University, 1981; F-16-7-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Radio-television-film 880e - seminar in international communications - Dallas Smythe and Tran Van Dinh, instructors, 1981; F-16-7-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Radio-television-film 383 - comparative broadcasting systems, 1980 - 1982; F-16-7-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - General teaching correspondence, 1980 - 1982; F-16-7-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Radio-television-film 860 - public policy, 1982; F-16-7-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Radio-television-film 880 - seminar in international communication - Dallas Smythe and Tran Van Dinh, instructors, 1982; F-16-7-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Temple University courses, 1982; F-16-7-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 444, 1978 - 1982; F-16-7-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Teach-in on Reaganomics - Temple University, 1982; F-16-7-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, 1977 - 1983; F-16-7-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, 1983; F-16-7-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 240 - the political economy of communications, summer, 1983, F-16-7-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 240 - political economy of communications, fall 1983, F-16-7-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, spring 1984, F-16-7-0-0-49 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, fall 1984, F-16-7-0-0-50 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 856 - political economy of the radio spectrum, 1976 - 1985; F-16-7-0-0-51 (Archival box - standard 16-45)
  - Communications 240 - political economy of communications, spring 1985, F-16-7-0-0-52 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 240 - political economy of communications, fall 1985, 1983 - 1985; F-16-7-0-0-53 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, spring 1985, 1984 - 1985; F-16-7-0-0-54 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of international communications, fall 1985, F-16-7-0-0-55 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 240 - political economy of communications, fall 1986, F-16-7-0-0-56 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Political economy of communications - class outlines and take-home exams, 1977 - 1986; F-16-7-0-0-57 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 444 supplementary material, 1962 - 1987; F-16-7-0-0-58 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 794D - communications and the third world - Ohio State University, 1987; F-16-7-0-0-59 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 860E - political economy of communications - Ohio State University, 1987; F-16-7-0-0-60 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 444 working file, 1987; F-16-7-0-0-61 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 444 - political economy of communications - backup, 1987; F-16-7-0-0-62 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 448 - telecommunications in North America, spring 1987, 1985 - 1987; F-16-7-0-0-63 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - Communications 240 - political economy of communications, 1980 - 1987; F-16-7-0-0-64 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
  - General course materials - Hawaii, 1970 - 1987; F-16-7-0-0-65 (Archival box - standard 16-46)
- Research files, 1943 - 1992; F-16-8; 1.64 m of textual records
  During his work as a professor at various universities, Smythe engaged in research in a variety of areas in the field of communications. Smythe also organized and participated in a number of conferences on communications and other topics.
  Series consists of records arising from Smythe's research activities and conference participation. Series includes correspondence, research articles, notes, and other materials.
  - Conferences, 1966 - 1987; F-16-8-1; 38 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of records arising from Smythe's participation in various conferences. Subseries includes correspondence, notes, articles, agendas, conference proceedings, planning materials (such as address lists and schedules), and other materials. The majority of the files relate to conferences organized by the International Association of Mass Communications Research (IAMCR).
    - Communications symposium - Regina, Saskatchewan, 1967; F-16-8-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - "Mass media and international understanding" symposium in Ljubljana, Yugoslavia, 1966 - 1968; F-16-8-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - "Conference on the legal problems of international communications" in Ottawa, Ontario, 1968 - 1969; F-16-8-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - American Society of International Law - panel on international telecommunications policy, 1968 - 1970; F-16-8-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - International Association of Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) meeting on communications satellites in Constance, Germany, 1970; F-16-8-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - International Association for Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) general assembly in Buenos Aires, Argentina, 1971; F-16-8-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - UNESCO meeting of experts on mass communications and society in Montreal, Quebec, 1969 - 1972; F-16-8-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - Trip to Tampere, Finland; Leipzig, East Germany; Moscow, U.S.S.R.; Belgrade, Yugoslavia; and Paris, France, 1971 - 1973; F-16-8-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 16-47)
    - International Association for Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) conference in Leipzig, East Germany, 1974; F-16-8-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - International Association for Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) tenth general assembly in Leicester, England, 1976; F-16-8-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - International Association for Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) eleventh general assembly in Warsaw, Poland, 1978; F-16-8-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - International Association for Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) proposed Communication Satellite and Technology Section, 1978 - 1979; F-16-8-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - International Association for Mass Communications Research (IAMCR) Political Economy Section meeting in Caracas, Venezuela, 1979 - 1980; F-16-8-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - Canadian Institute of International Affairs conference in Toronto, Ontario, 1984; F-16-8-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - Elections in the Americas conference, 1984; F-16-8-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - World Association for Christian Communications panel meeting in London, England, 1984 - 1985; F-16-8-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - Telecommunications research policy conference in Airlie, Virginia, 1985; F-16-8-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - Centre on Transnational Cultures meeting "New information technologies and cultural policies" in Lima, Peru, 1985; F-16-8-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 16-48)
    - International conference on liberation theology, 1986; F-16-8-1-0-19 (Archival box - small 16-49)
    - First Canberra conference on international communications, 1986; F-16-8-1-0-20 (Archival box - small 16-49)
    - Seminar on the socio-economic impact of new communications technologies held in Mexico, 1987; F-16-8-1-0-21 (Archival box - small 16-49)
    - International Communication Association - Congress of the International Society for Intercultural Education, Training, and Research in Montreal, Quebec, 1982 - 1987; F-16-8-1-0-22 (Archival box - small 16-49)
  - Subject files, 1943 - 1990; F-16-8-2; 51 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of records compiled by Smythe to support his research interests. Subseries includes lecture notes, addresses, photocopied monographs, notes, reports, and other materials. Records are organized into subject based files, including topics such as postal service, fax technology, the radio and television industries, newspapers and printing, media regulation, the peace movement, and other subjects.
    - Colour television, 1954; F-16-8-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Movies, 1950 - 1958; F-16-8-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Theatre - economics, 1949 - 1959; F-16-8-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Book, magazine, and newspaper publishing, 1945 - 1961; F-16-8-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Radio broadcasting, 1947 - 1961; F-16-8-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Television, 1949 - 1963; F-16-8-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Freedom of the press, 1946 - 1965; F-16-8-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Fax technology, 1948 - 1966; F-16-8-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 16-50)
    - Postal service, 1949 - 1966; F-16-8-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Fascism - political value, 1956 - 1967; F-16-8-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Telegraph, 1943 - 1969; F-16-8-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Broadcasting 1/2, 1966 - 1970; F-16-8-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Broadcasting 2/2, 1966 - 1970; F-16-8-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Negroes in the mass media, 1946 - 1973; F-16-8-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Public opinion, 1949 - 1973; F-16-8-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 16-51)
    - Cultural realism, cultural screens, 1953 - 1974; F-16-8-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 16-52)
    - Cultural industry, 1960 - 1975; F-16-8-2-0-17 (Archival box - standard 16-52)
    - Newspapers and printing, 1947 - 1975; F-16-8-2-0-18 (Archival box - standard 16-52)
    - Media regulation 1/2, 1958 - 1978; F-16-8-2-0-19 (Archival box - standard 16-52)
    - Media regulation 2/2, 1958 - 1978; F-16-8-2-0-20 (Archival box - standard 16-52)
    - Communications, 1959 - 1983; F-16-8-2-0-21 (Archival box - standard 16-53)
    - Economics and development, 1961 - 1981; F-16-8-2-0-22 (Archival box - standard 16-53)
    - Deregulation of radio, 1965 - 1981; F-16-8-2-0-23 (Archival box - standard 16-53)
    - Peace - notes and correspondence, 1965 - 1985; F-16-8-2-0-24 (Archival box - standard 16-53)
    - Peace - articles, 1960 - 1985; F-16-8-2-0-25 (Archival box - standard 16-53)
    - Centre for International Research on Communication and Information Technology (CIRCIT), 1989 - 1990; F-16-8-2-0-26 (Archival box - standard 16-53)
  - Research for publications, 1949 - 1992; F-16-8-3; 75 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of records produced and compiled by Smythe in preparation for his various publications. Subseries includes lecture notes, drafts, correspondence, reference material, and other records. Included are research materials for Smythe's articles on China, his book Dependency Road, and his unfinished book on a theory of communications.
    Files are arranged for the most part in chronological order, with related files grouped together, such as files regarding Smythe's trips to China, his book Dependency Road, and his last unpublished work.
    - Competition in broadcasting, [ca 1950] - [ca 1959]; F-16-8-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - Political effects of communications, 1950 - 1951; F-16-8-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - Tendencies toward a unified communication system, 1953; F-16-8-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - Telephone, 1949 - 1954; F-16-8-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - Postal rates, 1957; F-16-8-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - "Distant hills are greener" project, 1958 - 1959; F-16-8-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - "Empire" project, 1961 - 1962; F-16-8-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - Harper-Bell study, 1962; F-16-8-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - The U.S. and Us, 1968; F-16-8-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - McLuhan, 1966 - 1978; F-16-8-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - China - notes 1/2, 1969 - 1976; F-16-8-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - China - notes 2/2, 1969 - 1976; F-16-8-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 16-54)
    - China - lectures, 1972 - 1977; F-16-8-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - China - correspondence, 1970 - 1979; F-16-8-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - China - second trip, 1979; F-16-8-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - International Peace Research Association (IPRA), 1980 - 1981; F-16-8-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - Ideology, technology, and the development of communications, 1983; F-16-8-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - Transnational Research Institute for Policy (TRIP), 1983 - 1984; F-16-8-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - Review of: "Communication and class struggle" (Siegelaub and Mattelart), 1984; F-16-8-3-0-19 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - The State, 1984 - 1986; F-16-8-3-0-20 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - Review of The Heavens and the earth: a political history of the space age (McDougall), 1961 - 1987; F-16-8-3-0-21 (Archival box - standard 16-55)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 1, 1978 - 1989; F-16-8-3-0-22 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 2, 1964 - 1979; F-16-8-3-0-23 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 3, 1961 - [ca 1979]; F-16-8-3-0-24 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 4, 1978 - 1987; F-16-8-3-0-25 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 5, 1970 - 1987; F-16-8-3-0-26 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 6, 1979 - 1985; F-16-8-3-0-27 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 7, 1973 - 1986; F-16-8-3-0-28 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Dependency Road - chapter 8, 1977 - 1986; F-16-8-3-0-29 (Archival box - standard 16-56)
    - Notes for "On critical theory and the political economy of communications", 1963 - 1989; F-16-8-3-0-30 (Archival box - standard 16-57)
    - Training programme for senior and middle level officers of Third World countries for International Telecommunications Union conferences, 1985 - 1989; F-16-8-3-0-31 (Archival box - standard 16-57)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - articles, 1975 - 1987; F-16-8-3-0-32 (Archival box - standard 16-57)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - 1990 drafts 1/2, F-16-8-3-0-33 (Archival box - standard 16-57)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - 1990 drafts 2/2, F-16-8-3-0-34 (Archival box - standard 16-58)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - 1991 drafts, F-16-8-3-0-35 (Archival box - standard 16-58)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - revisions 1/2, 1987 - 1991; F-16-8-3-0-36 (Archival box - standard 16-58)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - revisions 2/2, 1987 - 1991; F-16-8-3-0-37 (Archival box - standard 16-58)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - notes, 1988 - 1992; F-16-8-3-0-38 (Archival box - standard 16-58)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - correspondence, 1989 - 1992; F-16-8-3-0-39 (Archival box - standard 16-58)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - correspondence and critiques 1/2, 1989 - 1992; F-16-8-3-0-40 (Archival box - small 16-59)
    - Smythe's last unpublished work - correspondence and critiques 2/2, 1989 - 1992; F-16-8-3-0-41 (Archival box - small 16-59)